Okay so today's דף *daf* is ז *zayin* 7 and we start
at the very, very bottom of ח *chet* עמוד ב *amud bais*.
We're dealing with interpreting the statement of רב Rav *Rav* that a
egg is only when it comes out is it finished and we
wanted to know what that meant. So the last thing the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* thinks it might mean is that it's only after it's
been laid that it's possible, assuming it's a fertilized egg,
possibly hatch a chick. But if it was taken out of the
mother, if the mother was שחט shacht *shechted* and an egg was
found inside of her body, then even if it's fertilized it would
not hatch a chick. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says למאי נפקא
מינה L'mai nafka mina, *l'mai nafka mina*. Somebody could check on Wikipedia
and see if this is correct, I have no idea. למאי נפקא
מינה lemai nafka mina? *l'mai nafka mina* says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*,
what practical הלכה halakha *halachic* difference does that make, that interesting little
fact? So it says למקח וממכר *l'mekach umimkar* for business deals. יהודה
*Yehuda* אמר להו *amar lehu*, somebody was saying to, going around and
like in the marketplace and saying to them, to people, דפחייא למאן
*d'pachya l'man*, who has for me eggs that have been, that have
been fertilized? Okay,
so רש''י Rashi *Rashi* says פחייא *pachya* means like a cooing, eggs
that have somehow indicated eggs that have been laid, you know. Well,
רש''י Rashi *Rashi* sounds like from a hen that had been cooing
while she lays an egg. Somehow, who has eggs that have been
laid? דבו ליה ביעי דשחוטה *davu leh beyei d'shchuta*, they gave him,
so פחייא *pachya* doesn't have to mean fertilized, who has eggs that
have been laid? So somebody sold him eggs without telling him that
he was doing this, eggs from an animal that was found inside
of a שחט shacht *shechted*, of a שחט shacht? *shechted* hen. אתא
לקמיה דרבי אמי Ata lekamei de-Rabbi Ammi, *ata l'kamei d'Rabi Ami*, so
then he came to רבי אמי Rabbi Ammi. *Rabi Ami*, I'm not
sure somehow he found out after the sale had been completed and
he wanted to get his money back. אמר להו *amar lehu*, he
said to them, to the merchant, מקח טעות mekach ta'ut. *mekach taus*,
it was a false sale, a sale under false pretenses. I mean
תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* doesn't actually mean you know false pretenses like intentional,
although that probably sounds like it was the case, but מקח טעות
mekach ta'ut *mekach taus* means it was an error, like even an
honest error could be a מקח טעות mekach ta'ut. *mekach taus*. Anyway,
so it is a, it is a purchase in error and הדר
*hadar* and it reverse, and it's reversed, give the egg back, get
the money back. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says פשיטא pshita, *pshita*,
obvious! He explicitly said he wanted laid eggs, so obviously it was
a מקח טעות *mekach taus*. No. מהו דתימא *mahu d'teima*, I might
have thought האי לחיואי גבאי *hai lachivei gavai*, maybe he wanted the
eggs to eat, not to hatch chicks. אמינא amina ליה *amina leh*,
and why did he say laid eggs? So משום דשפירא *mishum d'shafra*
because they're more complete, meaning not because he wanted them, you know,
for hatching chicks but just a laid egg is a further day
of completion than an unlaid egg. So what, it's still not what
he was asking for. So למאי נפקא מינה *l'mai nafka mina*, so
what would there be the difference? למיתיב ליה ביני ביני *lemeisiv leh
beini beinei*, so the whole sale wouldn't be an error, you'd have
to pay him for the difference but it wouldn't be like the
whole sale would be an error. קא משמע לן Kamashma lan *kama
shma lan* that if somebody is looking for laid eggs, we need
to assume that that means that he wants them for hatching chicks,
again they would also have to have been fertilized but okay. And
therefore the whole thing is fundamentally a sale in error, which means
you know, not every mistake means that the sale is reversible.
Sometimes there's a question of overcharging, right, so if you overcharge beyond
a certain amount it's reversible, less than a certain, you know, less
than that amount it's not reversible but you get your money back.
But there's also other cases, let's say I go to, you know,
to the new Porsche dealership there and I buy this Porsche and
I said, you know, and I want this particular CD package with
it. And they go ahead and they sell it to me and
they gave me a different CD package with it. So can I
make the whole sale void? You know, even though I had a
certain request, some requests are not seen as central to the, you
know, to my intention that it would mean without that I never
wanted to buy it, the whole thing was a mistake. So yeah,
there was a, there was an error in the sale and I'm
entitled to get the difference or entitled to get you replace my
CD package with the other CD package, but it doesn't mean that
fundamentally there was no דעת *daas* to buy it under those circumstances.
You go to a different Porsche dealer for your second Porsche.
Exactly. So, so here too, if my basic point was I wanted
to hatch chicks, so then fundamentally it was the exact wrong object
I was looking for according to this statement of רב Rav *Rav*
that I can't hatch chicks if they haven't been laid. But if
it's just that I wanted them to eat, but I thought I
was buying extra-large and I bought large, so that's not such a
fundamental difference, you give me back the difference in price. Okay, yes.
How much of that is what a reasonable person would interpret your
question to be versus what you actually meant? You understand?
So that's a good question, right, and about, and about whether you
say הולכין בממון אחר הרוב *holchin bemamon achar harov* and how much
we could assume, how, yeah, so that's an excellent question. Like, like
how much does that have to be self-evident, you know, in terms
of, in terms of how people would have interpreted and so on.
Generally, yes, we would have assumed that there has to be, it
has to be reasonably self-evident in the context of that case, otherwise
it's like דברים שבלב *devarim shebelev* and אין הולכין בממון אחר הרוב
*ein holchin bemamon achar harov* and so on. Okay, now that we've
have... cases like this, we're going to digress a little and have
similar cases, so let's take a look. ההוא דאמר להו,
somebody who's going around and saying, בי דכרי למאן? Bei dichrei leman?
בי דכרי למאן? Bei dichrei leman?
So eggs of a male, males don't lay eggs, but it means
eggs that were laid by a hen that had been fertilized, that
had mated with a male. יהבו ליה בי
דספנא מארעא. Yovlei bei de-safna me-ara. They gave him eggs that had
come from friction from the ground, which means not fertilized, eggs that
were just רש"י Rashi, says buried in the ground, eggs that were
laid on themselves without a male. Okay. אתא לקמיה דרבי
אמי, so he came to רבי אמי. אמר להו מקח טעות והדר.
Amar lehu mekach ta'ut ve-hadar. It's a false sale and it reverses.
Thank you so much. It's a false sale and it reverses. So
the גמרא Gemara says פשיטא, obviously you are asking for fertilized eggs.
No, מהו דתימא האי לאכילה קא בעי, Ma d'teima hai le-achila ka
ba'ei, maybe even when you want fertilized eggs, you wanted them for
eating, being bad זבחא zivcha because then if you found like a
blood spot it would be אסור, assur, but hopefully you were going
to get them before they had a blood spot. Okay. והא דקאמר
דדכרא, Ve-ha de-ka'amar de-dichra, so why did you want them to be
fertilized? משום דשמינן טפי, Mishum de-shaminan tvei, maybe he thought they were
like fattier eggs, they were better quality, but it was still all
about eating them. למאי נפקא מינה, in that case the difference would
be למיתבי ליה ביני ביני lemeisvei lei beinei beinei to pay the
difference in price, but it wouldn't be fundamentally a bad sale. קא
משמע לן that that's not the case, that if you're asking for
fertilized eggs it's because you really want fertilized eggs because you want
that you want to hopefully raise chicks. So, ואי בעית אימא, ve-i
ba'it eima, and if you want I can tell you, מה. mah.
Okay, so that's one answer for מקח טעות. It is, because we
have to assume you wanted to raise them as chicks. You wanted
to hopefully hatch chicks out of it. Okay, so that's one explanation
of what it means when it comes out and it's done, which
is that only after it's been laid can it have the potential
of chicks hatching, assuming it's been fertilized. Now, another explanation of what
this phrase means. ואי בעית אימא, Ve-i ba'it eima, we're leaving the
מקח טעות world. If you want I can tell you, מאי עם
יציאתה
נגמרה, mai im yetziata nigmera, what does it mean when it comes
out it's complete? עם יציאת רובן
נגמרה, im yetziat ruban nigmera, it's considered complete when already the majority
comes out. וכדרבי יוחנן, U-ke-Rabbi Yochanan, what's the relevance of that? For
the following הלכה halakha of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. דאמר רבי יוחנן
ביצה שיצא רובה מערב יום טוב וחזרה מותרת לאכלה ביום טוב. De-amar
Rabbi Yochanan beitza she-yatza rubah me-erev Yom Tov ve-chazrah muteret le-achlah be-Yom
Tov.
Back to our basic question of an egg born on יום טוב.
Yom Tov. So if it was, right, if the majority came out
before יום טוב Yom Tov and then it finished being laid after
sunset, then it is considered to be already have been laid from
the day before, and it is not מוקצה, muktzeh, it is fine
or not whatever problem a laid egg is because it's like it
was already born from the day before.
ואיכא דאמרי, Ve-ika de-amri, and some say, מאי עם יציאתן
נגמרה, mai im yetziatan nigmera, what does it mean when it comes
out it's complete? עם יציאת כולן נגמרה, im yetziat kulan nigmera, same
point about when is it considered born for the הלכות halakhot of
ביצה שנולדה ביום טוב, beitza she-nolada be-Yom Tov, but to tell you
the exact opposite of what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said. עם יציאתה
means when it fully comes out. Only when it fully comes out
is it born. עם יציאת כולן נגמרה. עם יציאת כולן
אין, im yetziat kulan in, only when it fully comes out, אבל
רובה לא, aval rubah lo, but not the majority. ולאפוקי מדרבי יוחנן,
U-le-afkuei me-de-Rabbi Yochanan, specifically to reject the position of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi
Yochanan. Okay, so those are now two explanations. The second the final
one, you know, or one of the two possibilities of the final
one probably makes more sense that רב Rav, was bothered to tell
us a הלכה halakha related to the משנה mishna of when is
an egg that's born permitted on יום טוב Yom Tov or forbidden
on יום טוב, Yom Tov, rather than this question of מקח טעות.
And according to this, he's either telling us either it all has
to come out or the majority of it has to come out,
but anyway you need to define exactly when it's considered to be
laid for the הלכה halacha that it was laid on ערב יום
טוב erev Yom Tov and therefore מותר mutar on יום טוב. Yom
Tov.
Yes, we had that whole week at the ישיבה yeshiva on start-of-life
issues. I don't remember this סוגיא sugya ever read.
Yeah, no, because there's plenty of הלכות halakhot about when a human
child is born and it talks about יצא רובה yatza rubah and
there's a question about when, you know, ראשה ורובה, rosha ve-rubah, ראשה
ורובה. rosha ve-rubah. So those are הלכות, halakhot, there is parallel, yes,
but of course, you know, but
different specifics, but yes, but when is something considered born? Absolutely. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay. גופא. Gufa. Now, let's get back to the other thing we
brought up in this discussion, that if the eggs were in the
hen, and again the hen was set aside for eating, then certainly
not a problem of a laid egg, it's part of the hen,
all part of the same food, and therefore it's permissible. השוחט את
התרנגולת, Ha-shocheit et ha-tarnegolet, he slaughtered a hen, ומצא
בה ביצים גמורות. u-matza bah beitzim gemurot. I'm sorry, that was one
thing we said. The other thing we said is now moving beyond
the מוקצה muktzeh point is when are they considered part of the
hen and considered meat, and when are they considered separate from the
hen and not considered meat for the הלכות halakhot of בשר בחלב.
basar be-chalav. Okay, so let's take a look. גופא. Gufa. השוחט את
התרנגולת, Ha-shocheit et ha-tarnegolet, he slaughtered a hen, ומצא בה ביצים
גמורות, u-matza bah beitzim gemurot, you find complete eggs. Now תוספות Tosafos
says the גירסא girsa probably is incomplete, as we're about to say,
but there's some degree near completion. רש"י Rashi says they don't have
a shell yet, but the white is still or the shell hasn't
hardened, but the white is is is- complete. In that case, מותרות
לאוכלן בחלב, mutaros leecholan b'cholov, they could be eaten with milk, although
they are not considered the meat, part of the meat of the
hen. רבי יעקב אומר, Rabbi Yaakov omer, Rabbi Yaakov says, if they
were still intertwined with the sinews, אסורות, asuros, they are forbidden. Again,
I don't know exactly the different stages of what a egg developing
in the inside of a mother of a hen looks like. But
he says at that stage where they're still intertwined with sinews, they're
considered to be essentially part of the meat of the mother and
they're not yet independent and and therefore they are forbidden to eat
with milk. Okay, so now let's let's take a look at this.
It helped us mark what the תוספות Tosfos was, wasn't it,
or whether you were allowed to have, you know, birds, where I
was assuming chicken is אסור asur with milk. Okay, so גמרא Gemara
says like this. מאן תנא להא דתנו רבנן? Man tanna lehada detannu
rabbanan? So who is the author of the following ברייתא? braisa? האוכל
מנבלת עוף טהור. Haochel minivlas of tahor. Now there's a הלכה halacha
that besides the fact that it's not kosher, a dead bird that
hasn't been shechted, but if it's a dead bird of a kosher
species that hasn't been shechted, besides that it's נבילה, neveilah, there's a
הלכה halacha that you become טמא tamei when you eat it. A
very strange category, normally you become טמא tamei when you touch things,
minimally if not in other ways as well. Here when you touch
this dead carcass of this dead, you know, chicken, you're not טמא,
tamei, but if you swallow it when it's down when it's sort
of in your throat, then you become טמא. tamei. But it's only
when you eat מנבלתה minivlasah from its carcass, which is understood to
be the meat of it. Okay, so this is going to be
another area where it's going to matter what do we define as
part of the meat of this bird and not part because only
when you swallow a כזית kezayis of the meat or a כביצה
kebeitzah of the meat, excuse me, only then do you become טמא.
tamei. So let's take a look.
האוכל מנבלת עוף טהור. Haochel minivlas of tahor. You eat from the
carcass of a kosher bird, but a non-shechted carcass. So מן השלל
של ביצים, min hashalal shel beitzim, if you eat from the cluster
of eggs, unlaid eggs, but they're, you know, they're distinct, they're a
cluster of eggs. Or מן העצמות min ha'atzamos or the bones, מן
הגידים min hagidim or the sinews, and here we're assuming the sinews
don't have don't have any taste to them so they're not considered
meat. ומן הבשר שנתלש מן החי umin habasar shenitlash min hachai or
it is from the meat, from the flesh, but it was torn
off when it was alive, it was not part of the flesh
when it died. So in all those cases טהור. tahor. Not necessarily
are you allowed to do it, you can't go to eat בשר
מן החי, basar min hachai, but you are do not become טמא.
tamei. You only become טמא tamei when you eat from the meat
of the dead carcass. מן האשכול של ביצים min ha'eshkol shel beitzim
however, if you ate it from the ovary sac, מן הקורקבן min
hakorkevan or from the crop, ובני מעיין uvnei me'ayin or from the
or from the intestines, או שהמחה את החלב וגמעו oshehi'imcha et hacheilev
ugemao or you sort of liquefied the fat of it and you
swallowed it, טמא, tamei, you are טמא. tamei. So even though that's
maybe it's it's liquefied, you would think it's different, all those are
considered the meat. But what do you see though? You see that
the cluster of eggs as opposed to the ovaries is not considered
the meat. So the גמרא Gemara says מאן תנא מן השלל של
ביצים טהור? man tanna min hashalal shel beitzim tahor? So who is
the who is the author of that position that the cluster of
eggs inside of the mother is you are טהור tahor which means
i.e. it's not meat? So גמרא Gemara says אמר רב יוסף דלא
כרבי יעקב, amar Rav Yosef delo k'Rabbi Yaakov, not like רבי יעקב.
Rabbi Yaakov. דרבי יעקב אמר אם היו מעורות בגידים אסורות. deRabi Yaakov
amar im hayu me'uros begidim asuros. He said if it's still intertwined
with the various with the sinews, it is forbidden and since this
categorically says if the cluster of eggs is not is not meat,
is not a problem, clearly that's not רבי יעקב. Rabbi Yaakov. רבי
יעקב Rabbi Yaakov would have a problem sometimes if it's still intertwined
with the cluster. So the גמרא Gemara says דאי כרבי יעקב הא
אמר אם היו מעורות בגידים אסורות. de'i k'Rabbi Yaakov ha'amar im hayu
me'uros begidim asuros. רבי יעקב Rabbi Yaakov says if it's intertwined it's
forbidden. So אמר ליה אביי, amar lei Abaye, so אביי Abaye said
back to רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, מנאיי, minai, how do you know
that's true? דילמא עד כאן לא קאמר רבי יעקב התם אלא לעניין
איסורא. dilma ad kan lo ka'amar Rabbi Yaakov hasam ella le'inyan issura.
Maybe רבי יעקב, Rabbi Yaakov, look, in principle he thinks that when
they're, you know, he would not say that they're meat. He would
agree that even if they're intertwined with the sinews once they're at
a certain stage of completion they're not considered meat. But he's being
strict. He's saying when it comes to the הלכה halacha. בשר בחלב,
basar b'chalav, you know we have a lot of stringencies with בשר
בחלב. basar b'chalav. So we'll consider this to be meat as well.
It's true really technically it's not meat but for בשר בחלב basar
b'chalav we'll be strict, don't eat it with meat. לעניין איסורא. le'inyan
issura. אבל
לעניין טומאה לא. aval le'inyan tumah lo. But when it comes to
the question of being making you טמא, tamei, we're going to go
by the עיקר הלכה ikkar halacha and it won't be meat and
we won't make you טמא. tamei. Right? וכי תימא לעניין טומאה נמי
נגזור? vekhi teima le'inyan tumah nami nigzor? So if we're being strict
more than we have to by the issue of בשר בחלב, basar
b'chalav, let's be strict by the issue of טומאה tumah and make
it like meat for the issue of טומאה. tumah. So the גמרא
Gemara says no, אפושי טומאה הוא, apushi tumah hu, that would just
spread טומאה tumah even more. The more things you make טמא, tamei,
the more you spread טומאה. tumah. So אפושי טומאה מדרבנן לא מפשינן.
apushi tumah miderabbanan lo mapshinan. And we don't want to rabbinically spread
טומאה tumah if we don't have to. Now of course the funny
thing is but there's a lot of times we make rabbinic טומאות.
tumos. So if you look at רש"י, Rashi רש"י's aware of this,
I don't know exactly what he answers, but here's what רש"י says,
last of the narrow
lines, אפושי טומאה מדרבנן לא מפשינן, apushi tumah miderabbanan lo mapshinan, ואף
על פי שגזרו בטומאות. ve'af al pi shegazru betumos.
Many times we make rabbinic טומאות tumos and גזירות, gezeiros, ליכא למימר
הכא נמי נגזור, leka l'meimar hacha nami nigzor, so
don't say do it here also. דלא ניחא לנו לאפושי בטומאה. delo
nicha lanu l'afshuei bitumah. We don't want to do a טומאה, tumah,
so at a certain point we say enough. So sometimes there's a
justifiable reason, but maybe here it's not so, you know, there's a
little bit put the brakes on. Anyway, the point being maybe he
makes a difference, maybe he's not if it were point that biblically
he considered it meat, you'd write, he'd have to say the same
הלכה. halacha. But maybe it's entirely rabbinic and maybe he's being strict
by בשר בחלב basar bechalav and not by טומאה. tumah. So maybe
in theory it could be רבי יעקב Rebbi Yaakov and רבי יעקב
Rebbi Yaakov is only being strict rabbinically. Okay. ואיכא דאמרי Ve'ika de'amri
and others say that the initial suggestion was the opposite. מאן תנא
מינה אשכול של ביצים טמא Man tana mina eshkol shel beitzim tamei
which started at the end of the משנה, Mishnah, who is the
author that says or at the end of the ברייתא, Braisa, that
if it's from the ovary sac it is טמא, tamei, it is
meat, אמר רב יוסף רבי יעקב היא, Amar Rav Yosef Rebbi Yaakov
hi, that's רבי יעקב Rebbi Yaakov because it's assuming that the second
part which says the ovary sac is considered meat means even after
the eggs have somewhat come out and they're still intertwined, that would
be in this category of אשכול של ביצים. eshkol shel beitzim. So
that would be רבי יעקב Rebbi Yaakov that אשכול של ביצים eshkol
shel beitzim is the category of eggs that are intertwined with the
sinews. דאמר אם היו מעורות בגידין אסורות. De'amar im hayu me'oros begidin
asuros. So אמר ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, so אביי Abaye said
back to רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, ממאי דאשכול מהנך דתליא באשכול? Mimay
d'eshkol mihanach detalya b'eshkol? What makes you think אשכול eshkol the ovary
sac means eggs that are out of the sac but are suspended
by it is this scenario of eggs that are growing but surrounded
by, you know, by sinews? דילמא אשכול גופיה, Dilma eshkol gufeh, maybe
it literally means the ovary sac that's so, that the, you know,
and only that if it's considered meat, but once the egg is
separated and growing it would not be. וכי תימא אשכול גופיה מאי
למימרא, Vechi teima eshkol gufeh mai l'meimra, if you say okay but
if it's the ovary sac itself what's the חידוש, chiddush, it's just
an inner organ, of course it's considered meat. No, there's a חידוש,
chiddush, מידי דהוה אקורקבן ובני מעיים, Midi d'hava akurkavan uvenei me'ayim, the
same way it had to mention that the crop and the intestines
were considered meat. Those are also obviously meat, so what's the
חידוש chiddush there? דאף על גב דבשר נינהו, De'af al gav d'basar
ninhu, even though obviously they're meat, כיוון דאיכא אינש דלא אכלי, keivan
d'ika inash delo achlei, since there are some people that are finicky
and wouldn't eat the crop and the gizzard, if you could imagine
that, and the intestines, so I might think that
איצטריכא לאשמועינן, itztaricha l'ashmoeinan, I might think that it's not considered that
enough meat or enough something that's edible that makes you טמא. tamei.
So he says right, so he says and that's the simple read
of the ברייתא Braisa that the ברייתא Braisa which says things are
meat is talking about things that are obviously meat but things that
are not normally eaten: the intestines, the crop, the ovary sac, those
things, even though they're not normally eaten, are considered food and meat
and they make you טמא. tamei. But what is
considered—but when the eggs actually have separated from the sac and are
still growing and developing, then it would not be meat and that's
against רבי יעקב. Rebbi Yaakov. רבי יעקב Rebbi Yaakov says at a
certain stage the eggs are still intertwined, they are meat. This indicates
the position not like רבי יעקב, Rebbi Yaakov, that they are not
meat even when they are still at a stage of being intertwined.
Okay. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. So that was the interesting הלכה. halacha
You see, once we're talking about eggs you got to talk about
a lot of things relating to eggs. So that's the הלכה Halacha
about when are the eggs considered to be meat or not and
again it's not, you know, in my mind I don't have a
clear picture of exactly what that cutoff point is but I don't
have a clear picture of what eggs look like in the—inside of
the hen anyway. But at a certain point even while they're still
intertwined and you know, they still might you know, they might they
might be part of the hen but they're not meat.
Yes, but what's the difference between the שלל shalal and the אשכול?
eshkol?
The שלל shalal is like the cluster of eggs that are growing
or an egg that is growing but it's not the אשכול—the eshkol
אשכול eshkol is the actual ovary sac.
And the שלל shalal is to refer to the cluster of the
eggs outside of it?
Yes, yes. Again I should have done my research so I could
tell you more, you know, just Charlie Workman, he would have—he would
have looked that up on Wikipedia.
But the גמרא Gemara doesn't even find it necessary to say אמינא
that since people aren't usually eating gizzards or whatever it is, that
you would be able to eat it with milk, that's taken for
granted. No, of course you couldn't, right no, but but same we're
not saying that for טומאה.
tumah. Yeah yeah, because טומאה tumah says אשר יאכל asher ye'achel so
maybe okay. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. Now we're going to get to
another interesting discussion about about laying eggs. כל שתשמישו ביום, Kol shetashmisho
bayom, any animal species, as we'll see including humans, that has sex
only by day, נולד ביום nolad bayom will only give birth in
the day or is born in the day literally.
כל שתשמישו בלילה, Kol shetashmisho balailah, any animal species that only has
sex at night, נולד בלילה nolad balailah also is only born at
night. כל שתשמישו בין ביום ובין בלילה, Kol shetashmisho bein bayom uvein
balailah, any species that has sex whether in the day and at
night, נולד בין ביום ובין בלילה nolad bein bayom uvein balailah will
be born in the day and in the night. So basically now
it doesn't mean when you when the mother happened to conceive happened
to
have— species
of that's nocturnal, I assume if it's nocturnal in its eating habits
it means it's nocturnal in its mating habits, so if it's a
nocturnal species it gives birth at night, if it's a diurnal, diurnal,
is that the daytime? Diurnal species it gives birth in the day,
and what's both?
Anybody?
Okay, both,
neither nocturnal nor diurnal, it gives birth in day and at night.
So the גמרא Gemara says what's an example of this?
כל שתשמישו ביום נולד ביום, kol shetashmisho bayom nolad bayom, says something
that's nocturnal in terms of its mating habits, or excuse me diurnal
in the day and it only gives birth in the day, זו
תרנגולת, zu tarnigolas, that's a hen. כל שתשמישו בלילה נולד בלילה, kol
shetashmisho balayla nolad balayla, anything that's nocturnal in its mating habits gives
birth at night, זו עטלף, zu atalef, that's a bat. כל שתשמישו
בין ביום ובין בלילה, kol shetashmisho bein bayom uvein balayla, anything
that mates in day and at night, נולד בין ביום ובין בלילה
nolad bein bayom uvein balayla gives birth day at night, so what's
that?
אדם וכל דדמי ליה, adam vechol dedami lei, humans and everything like
humans, which means I guess everything that's neither nocturnal nor diurnal. Okay,
אמר מר, amar mar, now let's talk about who cares about this.
What? Mammals? I assume it means mammals, but mammals? Like apes? Yeah,
but aren't like most mammals diurnal?
Like I mean, no? I mean, I think it's only like
bears, like hibernate.
Yeah, but I'm saying aren't like most, like before we had electric
lights, weren't we basically diurnal animals? Yeah.
So I don't exactly, anyway, okay, moving on. Okay, so I don't
know what's אדם וכל דדמי ליה. adam vechol dedami lei. I mean,
there are animals that prowl at night and so on, right?
Now we don't sleep.
But anyway, all right, anyway. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this. אדם וכל דדמי ליה. adam vechol dedami lei. אמר מר, amar
mar, כל שתשמישו ביום נולד ביום זו תרנגולת. kol shetashmisho bayom nolad
bayom zu tarnigolas. למאי נפקא מינה? What do I care about this
idea that chickens only give birth during the daytime or hens? So
לכדרב מרי בריה דרב כהנא, lechedrav mari brei de-rav kahana, like the
teaching of Rav Mari the son of Rav Kahana, דאמר רב מרי
בריה דרב כהנא, de-amar rav mari brei de-rav kahana, בדק בקנה של
תרנגולת, badak bekana shel tarnigolas, you checked your your
what's it called, your not pen, roost, your what's it called? Roost,
I guess. The roost of the hens מערב יום טוב, me-erev yuntif,
it was there, it was the night right before יום טוב yuntif
and you checked and there was no egg. ולא מצא בה ביצה,
velo matza bah beitza, there was no egg. And then it was
a second later it was already nightfall. ולמחר השכים ומצא בה ביצה,
ulemachar hishkim umatza bah beitza, and the next morning you woke up
and you found at 5:00 AM you got up and you checked
it and you saw there was an egg right there in the
in the nest or whatever it is, in the roost. So מותרת,
mutteres, it's permissible, which is crazy cause when did it lay birth?
It obviously birthed on the יום טוב. yom tov. But no, cause
you checked at 5:00 AM before daybreak, which means that it would
have to have given birth at night. But we've just said that
it's impossible for hens to lay eggs at night. So it must
be לא בדק, lo badak, did he check before nightfall? אימא לא
בדק שפיר, eima lo badak shapir, it must be you didn't check
well, because otherwise we'd have to say that it laid the egg
at night and we've just said it's impossible for hens to lay
eggs at night. ואפילו בדק שפיר, ve-afilu badak shapir, and even if
you checked well, I have an explanation. אימור יצא רובה וחזרה הוה,
eimur yatza rubah ve-chazra hava, what must have happened is must have
been the majority came out and then it went back in. So
therefore it wasn't there for you to see it, but technically it
had already given birth in the daytime, because the only other alternative
explanation was that it laid the egg at night and we know
that's not possible. וכדרבי יוחנן, ve-che-rabbi yochanan,
and like Rabbi Yochanan that said that would be considered already to
have been laid. So this brings you to a perfect example of
a pre-empirical world in which, you know, you go by the authority
of, you know, that you trust the sort of authority of tradition
or of what's written more than you trust your own eyes, right?
And you know, they this was clear like, you know, for like
for hundreds of years they went by like Galen's anatomy, you know,
from the Greek world, and even though when they would, you know,
which would describe what the inside of a person would be, and
even when they cut up a person and looked at the inside
and saw it didn't match what was in the book, obviously what
they were looking at was an anomaly, you know, but the book
was obviously right. You just discard the evidence, you know, so this
is sort of. Now, obviously people weren't like totally pre-empirical and people
did sort of see things with their own eyes, but it sort
of really shows you how, you know, how serious that that orientation
is. I don't know, somebody's got to look it up right now
in Wikipedia and tell me actually hens never give birth at night.
I don't know. But anyway, but here it says that if you
have to choose between whether it came out, I didn't check well
or it came out and went back in on the one hand,
or saying it gave birth at night on the other, I'll say
that it did not give birth at night and there's some other
explanation and actually I can eat the egg. So now the גמרא
Gemara says like this.
איני, eini, is this really true? והאמר רב יוסף בר שאול אמר
רב, ve-ha-amar rav yosef bar shaul amar rav, but didn't Rav Yosef
bar Shaul say in the name of Rav, בדק בקנה של תרנגולת
badak bekana shel tarnigolas מערב יום טוב ולא מצא בה ביצה. me-erev
Yom Tov ve-lo matza bah beitzah. You checked the roost of the
of the hens before יום טוב, Yom Tov, again right before יום
טוב, Yom Tov, so there was no time for it to be
laid, you know, after you checked it. You checked it from one
minute before שקיעה shkia till two minutes after שקיעה shkia and there
was no eggs. ולמחר דהשכים ומצא בה ביצה u-le-machar de-hishkim u-matza bah
beitzah and the next morning you woke up before daybreak and you
saw an egg, אסורה, asura, it's forbidden because it did lay at
night. The גמרא Gemara says no, התם בדספנא מארעא. hatam be-dasfna me-ara.
Ah, we have an explanation. It can lay an egg at night
if it's an unfertilized egg, right? This is all about when it
had sex. So it can lay an egg at night if it's
an unfertilized egg. It's only a fertilized egg that it will only
lay during the day. So the גמרא Gemara says אי הכי, i
hachi, if that's true, דרוב נמי מרי, de-rov nami mari, so you
lose your whole your whole קולא kula here because your whole scenario
oh I can assume it was the day before it's not true.
אימא מדספנא מארעא, eima mi-dasfna me-ara, maybe I have to assume that
this is an unfertilized egg, there goes your whole idea because you
can't just say oh it didn't happen at night, maybe it did
happen at night and maybe it was an unfertilized egg. He says
no, דאיכא זכר בהדה. de-ika zachar bahada. There's a rooster like around
in the neighborhood and therefore we have to assume if there's a
rooster walking around that it's not unfertilized. So the גמרא Gemara says
דאיכא זכר נמי אימא מדספנא מארעא, de-ika zachar nami eima mi-dasfna me-ara,
who cares that there's a rooster walking around, maybe it's still an
unfertilized egg and it was laid at night. אמר רבינא, Amar Ravina,
so Ravina says גמירי, gemiri, we have a tradition: כל היכא דאיכא
זכר לא ספנא מארעא. kol heicha de-ika zachar lo safna me-ara. As
long as there's a rooster around, it's not going to lay an
unfertilized egg, which could mean the rooster will mate with every available
hen or it could just mean that the hen when it knows
that there's a rooster around somehow its body will react and it
won't lay an egg without it being until it's fertilized. Anyway, so
that's a new principle that we've got. So therefore we have the
scenario that you can assume the egg was not overnight, not during
the night when there's a rooster in the neighborhood and then it
won't be it won't lay unfertilized eggs. One wonders if they did
empirical testing for this also. So the גמרא Gemara says ואד כמה,
ve-ad kama, how close does the rooster have to be to assume
it won't lay unfertilized eggs? So אמר רב גמדא משמיה דרב כל
היכא דשמע קוליה ביממא. amar Rav Gamda mishmei de-Rav kol heicha de-shama
kalei bi-ymama. As long as you can hear its voice or maybe
the hen can hear its voice in the daytime. Okay, because in
the daytime sounds travel don't travel as far as in the night,
but the daytime matters because it mates in the daytime. So as
long as in the daytime it's hearing that there's a rooster, it
will somehow body will react and it won't lay the egg and
it'll wait till it mates. But if it can't hear, hear the
crowing of the rooster, but if it can, then it'll lay the
egg without it being fertilized.
So עבד רב מרי עובדא עד שיתין בתי. avad Rav Mari uvda
ad shitin bati. Rav Mari paskened this way in a case where
the rooster was sixty houses away and he said that's still close
enough and therefore if the egg was laid, you know, there's a
question when the egg was laid, was it you know it seems
like it was laid overnight, we're going to say no, there was
a rooster in the neighborhood within sixty houses and therefore it has
to be a fertilized egg and therefore it could not have been
laid at night, it must have been laid from the day before.
Now one minute, ואיכא נהרא, ve-ika nahara, now let's say the rooster
is within sixty houses or whatever within the ability of its voice
to be heard but there's a river between it and the rooster,
how far will it go? Okay, it's like the גמרא Gemara says
אין אפוטרופוס לעריות, ein apotropos le-arayos, you know, so the גמרא Gemara
has a scenario like you can never be sure that you're protecting
people from actually having sex because of the strong יצר הרע. yetzer
hara. So here same question, how many obstacles do you think have
to be there and we still have to think that the rooster
will make sure to get together with the hen? So if there's
a river between them, לא עברה, lo avra, it won't cross over
the river. ואיכא גשרא ve-ika gishra but if there's a bridge, עברה,
avra, it'll go over. ואיכא מצרא ve-ika metzra if there's like a
like a like a like a no like a thin plank or
Rashi says like a rope you know like you would walk on
a plank and you'd sort of walk with holding onto a thin
rope on top. So then he says ואיכא מצרא לא עברה. ve-ika
metzra lo avra. It won't pass over that like thin little plank.
הוה עובדא ועברה אמצרא havah uvda ve-avra a-metzra and actually it did
walk over that thin plank. Okay, can't roosters can't hens walk on
like a wire? No? Am I thinking of something else? Maybe I'm
thinking of like just birds that rest on a wire. Can't they
fly? No, really? They like little hops, they can't really fly. Okay,
anyway,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: okay, now where are
we? Okay,
ובמאי אוקימתא, u-ve-mai okimta, let's just finish this point. ובמאי אוקימתא, u-ve-mai
okimta, what did you say the case was where you had to
where he checked the day before and you said it was a
problem, it might have been laid overnight? בדספנא מארעא be-dasfna me-ara when
it was unfertilized and therefore we have to assume it was laid
overnight. So the גמרא Gemara says מאי אריא בדק? mai irya badak?
So why did you say that he checked a minute before sunset?
כי לא בדק נמי ki lo badak nami even if he didn't
check. Now here's the question: I didn't check right before sunset, I
came to the the the rooster the next morning or the coop,
that's what you call it, the coop the next morning and I
and I saw that there was an egg. the morning of יום
טוב. Yom Tov. When was it laid? Was it laid overnight or
was it laid ערב יום טוב? Erev Yom Tov? I don't know.
What's the הלכה Halacha if I didn't check a minute before before
it became יום טוב? Yom Tov? Maybe it was laid from ערב
יום טוב? Erev Yom Tov? That's what the גמרא Gemara says. קצתו?
Kitzto? No, כי לא בדק אימא מאתמול הוי. ki lo badak eima
mei'etmol havei. If you don't know, here's a very important הלכה Halacha.
finally at the end of the whole discussion we're telling you let's
say you don't know when the egg was laid, right? You came
יום טוב Yom Tov morning, there was the egg, it's not clear:
was it laid overnight or was it laid from before it got
dark from ערב יום טוב? Erev Yom Tov? So it says if
you don't know then you can be lenient, it's a ספק, safek,
it's rabbinic and you'll be lenient. So the גמרא Gemara says: אי
הכי כי בדק נמי, ee hachi ki badak nami, so if that's
true even if you did check a minute before יום טוב Yom
Tov you should be lenient. Why? What could you be lenient about?
אימא יצתה רובה וחזרה
היא וכדרבי יוחנן? eima yatzta ruba v'chazra hi v'che-Rabbi Yochanan? Because maybe
even if you checked maybe the majority had already come out and
it went back in. So maybe we'll always be lenient and say
it had always been laid before יום טוב Yom Tov and went
back
in וכדרבי יוחנן. v'che-Rabbi Yochanan. דבי יוחנן d'Rabbi Yochanan says no, דרבי
יוחנן לא שכיח, d'Rabbi Yochanan lo shchiach, that's a very uncommon case.
So therefore here's a fascinating הלכה. halakha If the egg is born,
besides this funny idea that we have to assume it wasn't laid
at night if it was fertilized, but just a simple case: you
find an egg in your coop on יום טוב Yom Tov morning,
actually if you don't know it's מותר, muttar, unless you're certain it
was laid overnight. You know if there's a possibility it was already
laid from before יום טוב Yom Tov began then you can actually
be lenient. It can't be when you check you don't think that
רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan's possibility is not something that's a reasonable possibility
but if you didn't check and there's that possibility you can be
lenient. So the גמרא Gemara says, just to end up this point
on a not relevant point, ואמר רבי יוסי בן שאול אמר רב,
v'amar Rabbi Yose ben Shaul amar Rav, since it started with the
statement of רבי יוסי בן שאול Rabbi Yose ben Shaul in the
name of רב about the egg coming out and being completed etc.,
the גמרא Gemara says האי תומא שחיקא, hai tuma shechikha, if you
have ground garlic, so סכנתא לגלוייא, sakanata l'gluya, it is dangerous to
leave it uncovered. So completely other point. Now I just want to
say one last thing about, and I know there was a question
about this idea of you can be lenient if you don't know
when it was laid and assume it was ערב יום טוב, Erev
Yom Tov, it's a ספק לקולא. safek l'kula. So that makes sense,
ספק דרבנן לקולא. safek d'rabanan l'kula. But look at this little תוספות
Tosfos that reminds us of an earlier discussion. כי לא בדק אימא
מאתמול הוי. ki lo badak eima mei'etmol havei. תוספות Tosfos says ואם
תאמר והביצה דבר שיש לו מתירין, v'im tomar v'ha-beitzah davar she-yeish lo
matirin, wait a minute, the egg is something that will become permissible
after יום טוב Yom Tov you can eat it, so why should
we be lenient just because it's a doubt? We should say let's
be strict and wait till tomorrow. אם כן ספק לחומרא im kein
safek l'chumra you should be strict. יש לומר דשאני הכא משום דגרמי
פשיטא דמאורא שכיח דיולדת ביום יותר מבלילה. yesh lomar d'shani hacha mishum
d'garim p'shita d'me'ora shchiach d'yoledet bayom yoteir miba-layla. That even in unfertilized
cases most likely it was daytime anyway and therefore most likely it
was at night, so therefore we can be lenient. But what's relevant
about this תוספות Tosfos is he says this principle about being lenient
on rabbinic matters in a case of doubt, ספק דרבנן לקולא, safek
d'rabanan l'kula, doesn't necessarily apply if it is a דבר שיש לו
מתירין. davar she-yeish lo matirin. You could wait till tomorrow. I just
want to remind you, maybe I shouldn't because it was complicated when
we did it the first time, but the general principle of דבר
שיש לו מתירין, davar she-yeish lo matirin, something that will become permissible
later, is a principle that it's not בטיל, bateil, that if it
gets mixed up in other things like חמץ chametz on פסח Pesach
and right, then there's no ביטול. bittul. Whether that means that you
can't apply other leniencies like ספק דרבנן לקולא safek d'rabanan l'kula or
ספק ספיקא sfeik sfeika and so on is less clear but there
was an indication in the גמרא Gemara that even those other types
of leniencies don't apply to דבר שיש לו מתירין. davar she-yeish lo
matirin. So that's what תוספות is reminding us of and bringing this
up here. But the simple sense of the גמרא Gemara is that
no, it's a rabbinic matter, if you're not sure whether it was
from yesterday or today you can be lenient in this case and
say the egg is permissible. David you had a question from before.
I was just going to mention it's coincidence it talks about 60
hours and the idea of ביטול bittul being one-sixtieth?
Oh yeah that some number of 60 has a significant number? Yeah,
it's not exactly ביטול bittul but it's using the number of 60,
right right. Okay.
Why is it rabbinic?
Because the whole idea of the egg being forbidden, I mean if
it's מוקצה muktzah it's rabbinic and at the end the other things
we said like fruit that fell from a tree or liquids that
remember those other explanations are all rabbinic concerns. Okay, so let's take
a look.
No excuse me that רבי יוסי בן שאול אמר רב Rabbi Yose
ben Shaul amar Rav was this idea about checking the night before
about having been laid you know when we assume it was laid
at night. So that's another statement of רבי יוסי בן שאול אמר
רב Rabbi Yose ben Shaul amar Rav about this ground garlic. Now
we finally go beyond the case of the egg and we get
to the next line in the משנה Mishnah which is if you
remember the משנה Mishnah started with three debates of בית שמאי Beit
Shammai בית הלל Beit Hillel on יום טוב Yom Tov where בית
שמאי Beit Shammai was lenient and בית הלל Beit Hillel was strict.
And the second one actually is פסח Pesach related. What is the
minimum amount of bread and the minimum amount of sourdough שאור? se'or?
So sourdough is basically not edible but it's used for fermenting, it's
used for making dough. So that also is forbidden. You'll know the
Torah often switches between חמץ chametz and שאור se'or right? כל... it
says לא יראה לך חמץ chametz ולא יראה לך שאור se'or. בכל
גבולך שבעת ימים. Right, and it speaks about not eating חמץ chametz
and not eating שאור. se'or So בית שמאי Beit Shammai says, בית
הלל Beit Hillel says the amount, minimum amount for both of them
is כזית. kezayit. בית שמאי Beit Shammai says no, the minimum amount
for שאור se'or? is a כזית kezayit because that's powerful, that can
ferment other things, but the minimum amount of חמץ chametz. is actually
ככותבת, k'kotevet, like a pressed date, and therefore is actually a larger
size, which is lenient, means you don't transgress until you have more
חמץ. chametz? So let's take a look. The גמרא says yes.
Just did we come to a conclusion on the first one between
בית הלל Beit Hillel and בית שמאי? Beit Shammai?
Yeah, we go like בית הלל Beit Hillel in these cases. Yeah,
even though בית הלל Beit Hillel is more strict. Right.
Is the dry yeast in a package the same הלכה halakha as
שאור?
se'or No, I don't think so. What exactly is dry yeast in
a package? Is it?
It does what sourdough does.
I understand, but what is it?
Is it made from leavened bread?
No, it's not.
Okay, so probably it isn't. בית שמאי אומר שאור בכזית. Beit Shammai
omer se'or b'kezayit. מאי טעמא
דבית שמאי, mai ta'ama d'Beit Shammai, what's the reasoning of בית שמאי
Beit Shammai that says that there's different amounts? אם כן לכתוב רחמנא
חמץ. im ken lichtov Rachmana chametz. Why? He takes for granted that
שאור se'or is more strict because it can make other things, it
can leaven other things. So why did the תורה Torah have to
forbid שאור se'or. separate from חמץ? chametz Just tell me don't eat
חמץ chametz. or don't own חמץ. chametz ולא בעי שאור, v'lo ba'ei
se'or, you don't have to tell me not to eat or own
שאור. se'or ואנא אמינא, va'ana amina, I would say מה חמץ שאין
חימוצו קשה, ma chametz she'ein chimutzo kasheh, חמץ chametz, that its leavening
is not strong, it doesn't leaven other things, בכזית, b'kezayit, that obviously
goes by כזית kezayit because that's the normal minimum size especially relating
to things that are about eating. שאור שחימוצו קשה, se'or shechimutzo kasheh,
שאור se'or? which has powerful leavening powers, לא כל שכן, lo kol
sheken, certainly that would be forbidden. So שאור דכתב רחמנא למה לי?
se'or d'chtav Rachmana lama li? Why did the תורה Torah have to
also say don't own and don't eat שאור? se'or We'll see in
a minute whether owning and eating is the same, for now we'll
assume it's the same. למלפך l'malfatcha to tell you, שיעור שזה לא
כשיעור שזה, shiur shezeh lo k'shiur shezeh, that they're different categories, that
actually they're different amounts, and therefore the smallest size we have is
a כזית, kezayit, so that will give to שאור se'or because שאור
se'or is more powerful than חמץ, chametz? it'll be a little bit
more, it's not as powerful, the next logical size רש״י Rashi says
is a ככותבת. k'kotevet. Why is it next logical size? Because that's
the amount like we know from יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, you know,
that's the amount that actually is considered like to get settle you,
like a little bit fill you. So again relating to things that
are about eating, the next logical size after כזית kezayit which is
about the act of eating is the amount of a
ככותבת k'kotevet which sates you a little bit. Less than a ביצה?
beitzah? That's less than a ביצה. beitzah. Okay, so all that whole
thing got discussed in יומא Yoma its relationship to a ביצה, beitzah,
I'm not going there yet. Okay, so now. Okay, בית הלל Beit
Hillel what would בית הלל Beit Hillel say? Why do you have
to say both שאור se'or? and חמץ? chametz. How if why couldn't
you have learned one from the other? They would say צריכי, tzrichi,
you need to say both. דאי כתב רחמנא שאור, de'i chtav Rachmana
se'or, had it just said sourdough, הוה אמינא משום דחימוצו קשה, hava
amina mishum d'chimutzo kasheh, maybe that's forbidden because it has powerful leavening
power, אבל חמץ דאין חימוצו קשה, aval chametz d'ein chimutzo kasheh, אימא
לא, eima lo, maybe it wouldn't be prohibited to own סתם stam
bread. צריכא tzricha and it therefore has to tell me חמץ. chametz,
ואי כתב רחמנא חמץ, v'ei chtav Rachmana chametz, and if it had
just said חמץ, chametz why wouldn't I have said if חמץ chametz,
is forbidden certainly שאור? se'or. No, משום דראוי לאכילה, mishum d'ra'ui l'achila,
because it's fit to be eaten. So that makes that stronger than
שאור. se'or אבל שאור שאין ראוי לאכילה, aval se'or she'ein ra'ui l'achila,
sourdough which is not fit to be eaten, אימא לא, eima lo,
maybe it wouldn't be transgressed or you wouldn't transgress to the same
severity. צריכא, tzricha, so it's not so obvious which is higher than
which on some hierarchy or stringency. Each one has its stringent elements.
The שאור's se'or element is that it makes other things חמץ, chametz
and the חמץ chametz. element is that it's edible. So each one
is so you need to say both and they both do have
the same size. Okay, so now the גמרא says like this.
ובית שמאי לית להו דרבי זירא. u'Beit Shammai leit lehu d'Rabbi Zeira.
And now בית שמאי Beit Shammai doesn't hold of רבי זירא. Rabbi
Zeira. דאמר רבי זירא, d'amar Rabbi Zeira, רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira says
פתח הכתוב בשאור וסיים בחמץ. patach hakatuv b'se'or v'siyyem b'chametz. One verse
opened with שאור se-or. and ended with חמץ. hametz. למה לך lamma
lecha to tell you זה שאור זה חמץ, zeh se'or zeh chametz,
the same הלכה applies to both. What is this פסוק? pasuk? So
the פסוק pasuk is שבעת ימים שאור לא ימצא בבתיכם כי כל
אוכל מחמצת. shivat yamim se'or lo yimatzei b'vateichem ki kol ochel machmetzet.
Like what's the combination? For seven days don't have any sourdough in
your house because anybody who eats bread transgressed. So why is eating
bread related to not having sourdough? To tell you that they're all
the same, we're not making any distinctions between sourdough and bread, they're
all treated the same way.
למה לך זה שאור זה חמץ, lamma lecha zeh se'or zeh chametz,
there's no halakhic, not the same physical thing, but there's no halakhic
difference between the two. The גמרא says you know what you're right.
לעניין אכילה כולי עלמא לא פליגי, l'inyan achila kulei alma lo pligi,
when it comes to eating nobody debates, everybody says that you transgress
once you eat a כזית. kezayit. Okay, כי פליגי לעניין ביעור, ki
pligi l'inyan biyur,
what we're debating is the issue of destroying or to remove. frame
it, the prohibition of owning it. בית שמאי סברי לא ילפינן ביעור
מאכילה, Beis Shammai savri lo yalpinan biyur me-achila,
although they are equated when it comes to eating, we don't learn
the idea of destroying and prohibition of owning from eating. And even
though by eating they're treated the same, by owning they're treated different.
ובית הלל סברי, u-Beis Hillel savri, and בית הלל Beis Hillel holds:
ילפינן ביעור מאכילה. yalpinan biyur me-achila. No,
we do learn it. The same way by destroying they're the same,
the same way by eating they're the same, by destroying they're the
same and it's a כזית kezayis by everything. איתמר נמי, itmar nami,
it was also taught: אמר רבי יוסי בר חנינא, amar Rabbi Yose
bar Hanina, מחלוקת לענין ביעור. machlokes le-inyan biyur.
The debate is when it comes to destroying. That that's where בית
שמאי Beis Shammai goes a little bit easier on you when it
comes to חמץ. hametz אבל לענין אכילה, aval le-inyan achila, when it
comes to eating, דברי הכל זה וזה בכזית. divrei hakol zeh va-zeh
be-kezayis. Everybody would say it goes by a כזית. kezayis. תניא נמי
הכי, Tanya nami hachi, it's taught similar: ולא יראה לך חמץ ולא
יראה לך שאור. ve-lo yera-eh lecha hametz ve-lo yera-eh lecha se-or. So
that's
ממש mamash doubled it, the exact same prohibition by חמץ hametz and
שאור. se-or Why does it have to say it twice, two separate
prohibitions? זו מחלוקת שבין בית שמאי ובית הלל. Zo machlokes she-bein Beis
Shammai u-Beis Hillel. That's the debate of בית שמאי Beis Shammai and
בית הלל. Beis Hillel. שבית שמאי אומרים שאור בכזית וחמץ בככותבת. She-Beis
Shammai omrim se-or be-kezayis ve-hametz be-kakoseves. בית שמאי Beis Shammai says since
it has since it says two prohibitions, it's actually to tell you
a different amount, that that חמץ hametz you only transgress when you
own it when it's a ככותבת, kakoseves, but שאור already the size
of an olive. ובית הלל אומרים זה וזה בכזית, u-Beis Hillel omrim
zeh va-zeh be-kezayis, they're both the size of an olive. Okay, so
now we've basically gotten down that the whole debate is when it
comes to owning it. So it does not really tell us other
than this issue of חימוצו קשה himutzo kasheh conceptually why it should
be different. Why should owning be different than eating? So I'll just
tell you since we're almost on פסח, Pesach, so I'll give you
just a little a little insight into some basic question about the
idea of חמץ על פסח. hametz al Pesach. So there's a fascinating
question which is like: why does the תורה Torah say not to
own חמץ hametz in your house? Why not? So there's two explanations.
One explanation is that like the פסוק pasuk says: לא יראה לך
שאור שבעת ימים שאור לא ימצא בבתיכם כי כל אוכל מחמצת ונכרתה.
Lo yera-eh lecha se-or shivas yamim se-or lo yimatzei be-vateichem ki kol
ochel machmetzes ve-nichresah. Don't own it because if you'll own it you'll
come to eat it. And that's why ראשונים Rishonim say that even
when you do ביטול, bittul, the rabbis require you to destroy it.
And it's different from the fact like I'm allowed to own חזיר.
hazir. Why can I own חזיר? hazir? I can have חזיר hazir
in my fridge. Because חזיר, hazir, I know it's taboo, I know
to keep off. חמץ hametz which I eat the rest of the
year, it's not so taboo and on פסח Pesach I'll have some
חמץ hametz lying around, I'll forget I'll come to eat it. So
one explanation is the תורה Torah says don't eat it, it's the
תורה's Torah own safeguard. The rabbis are always making safeguards, here the
תורה's Torah making safeguards. Don't own it lest you come to eat
it. But there's another explanation. The other explanation is is that the
very nature of the יום טוב yom tov as חג המצות Chag
Ha-Matzos is a day in which, you know, חמץ hametz is in
contradiction to its identity as the חג המצות. Chag Ha-Matzos. So even
if you won't come to eat it, just having חמץ hametz, under
your possession is against what the whole theme of the day is,
which, you know, לא הספיק בצקם, lo hispik betzeikam, it's all about
מצה matzah and it's all about not having חמץ, hametz right? I
mean, you know, there's a people make a big thing about the
idea of getting rid of the חמץ hametz. in your life. That
it's not just maybe you'll come to eat it. Like the symbolic
idea of it's not about חמץ. hametz, So it seems that that
possibility opens I mean you could say both possibilities in בית הלל
Beis Hillel as well, but it seems like it opens up even
more in בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, because בית שמאי Beis Shammai actually
says that you can own a כזית kezayis of- not it's מותר,
muttar, but you don't transgress by owning a כזית kezayis of חמץ,
hametz, even though were you to eat it, you would transgress. But
he would say nevertheless to transgress for owning it, it has to
be more than the amount that if you were to eat it
would be a problem. So it seems to him that the idea
of owning is not directly related to the concern of eating. Right?
Is that clear? Because if it was all about the concern of
eating, then a כזית kezayis would be a problem. You'll pop it
in your mouth. No, somehow its presence is a problem. If you
want its presence to be a problem and not just you might
come to eat it, maybe you need a more substantial amount for
its presence to be a problem. So that's interesting in terms of
thinking about what is the issue of owning חמץ, what that prohibition
is about. Okay, now back to normal generic יום טוב. yom tov.
And the משנה Mishnah says if you שחט shacht a חיה ועוף,
chayah ve-of, a wild animal like a deer, wild species, or a
bird, and you have to cover the blood, so what do you
do? So בית שמאי Beis Shammai says you dig in the dirt
and you cover it, and בית הלל Beis Hillel says don't שחט
shacht. unless you already have the dirt ready. Okay, so that's a
little bit funny because it started by saying: What happens if you
did שחט? shacht? And בית הלל's Beis Hillel answer is: Well, you
shouldn't have שחט shacht it in the first place. Don't שחט. shacht
So what are we talking about? Are we talking about if you
did it or we talking about you're asking permission whether you're allowed
to do it? And that's what the גמרא asks.
השוחט דיעבד. Ha-shochet di-eved. In, yeah. I mean, דיעבד di-eved in, לכתחילה
lechatchila lo. So the משנה Mishnah starts by saying: What happens if
you did שחט? shecht You did it already, דיעבד. di-eved. It already
happened, not לכתחילה. lechatchila. And you want to know now that I've
done it, what am I allowed to do? ואימא סיפא, Ve-eima seifa,
but look at the end of this משנה. Mishnah. ובית הלל אומרים,
u-Beis Hillel omrim, בית הלל's Beis Hillel response to this question is:
I already שחט shecht it is: לא ישחוט, lo yishchot, don't שחט
shecht, it. That's not so helpful. בכלל. Bichlal. the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma sorry, that implies that the question is לכתחילה lechatchila and the
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma saying ישחוט, yishchot, you're allowed to שחט shecht.
לכתחילה. lechatchila. Even though it frames it as what happens if you
did שחט shecht it. So what are we talking about? Are we
talking about בדיעבד be-diavad or are we talking about לכתחילה? lechatchila?
So אמר הא לא קשיא, amar ha lo kashya, that's not difficult.
לא ישחוט ויכסה קאמר. lo yishchot v'yichaseh ka'amar. When בית הלל Beis
Hillel says don't שחט, shechted. they don't mean don't שחט. shecht They
mean don't you shouldn't
don't be involved in everything related to שחיטה shechita here. Don't finish
the שחיטה, shechita, don't cover it. Okay, so בית הלל Beis Hillel
is talking about
בדיעבד. be-diavad. Okay, and all right, so now you're saying בית הלל
Beis Hillel ובית שמאי u'Beis Shammai are debating בדיעבד. be-diavad. And בית
הלל Beis Hillel says even בדיעבד be-diavad don't do anything. אימא סיפא,
eima seifa, look at the very end of the משנה. Mishnah. ומודים
בית הלל ובית שמאי u'modim Beis Hillel u'Beis Shammai agree שאם שחט
she-im shachat that if you did שחט shecht? שיחפור בדקר ויכסה she-yachpor
b'deker v'yichaseh that you can dig with a with a like a
shovel and cover. So it's very clear in the end that they
agree בדיעבד. be-diavad. So clearly their argument is לכתחילה. lechatchila. מכלל דרישא
לאו בדיעבד הוא. mikh'lal d'reisha lav be-diavad hu.
So clearly where they're arguing it's not about you already did it
because בית הלל Beis Hillel say if you already did it, okay,
cover it already. So obviously they're arguing about לכתחילה. lechatchila. So what
do you do about the phrase השוחט? ha-shochet? So אמר רבא amar
Rava says רבא Rava הכי קאמר. hachi ka'amar.
השוחט שבא לימלך כיצד. ha-shochet she-ba l'himalekh keitzad. Not one who already
שחט. shecht, השוחט, ha-shochet, the the slaughterer, the butcher. Okay, השוחט ha-shochet
which is a funny read because a verb is missing. השוחט חיה
ועוף, ha-shochet chaya v'of, but it means one who wants to שחט
shecht חיה ועוף chaya v'of on יום טוב, Yom Tov, what do
you do? Okay, כיצד. אומר לו, keitzad omer lo, what do you
tell somebody who wants
to שחט? shecht בית שמאי אומרים Beis Shammai omrim אומר לו omer
lo, שחוט חפור וכסה. shechot chapor v'chaseh. Go ahead, שחט, shecht? dig
in the dirt, cover it. ובית הלל אומרים u'Beis Hillel omrim לא
ישחוט אלא אם כן היה לו עפר מוכן מבעוד יום lo yishchot
ela im kein haya lo afar muchan m'be'od yom unless you have
prepared dirt. So basically because the end of the משנה Mishnah makes
it clear that they agree בדיעבד be-diavad you're allowed to cover it,
they say that even though the phrase opens with השוחט, ha-shochet, the
question is are you allowed to do it לכתחילה? lechatchila? בית שמאי
Beis Shammai says you can שחט shecht. לכתחילה lechatchila even without prepared
dirt and בית הלל Beis Hillel says you cannot שחט shecht לכתחילה.
lechatchila.
רב יוסף אמר, Rav Yosef amar, now רב יוסף Rav Yosef says
it's going to sound like the same thing. הכי קאמר. hachi ka'amar.
השוחט שבא לימלך. ha-shochet she-ba l'himalekh. Somebody is coming to ask for
permission. Am I allowed to שחט? shecht If he wants to שחט.
shecht, כיצד keitzad. אומר לו, omer lo what do you tell him?
בית שמאי אומרים Beis Shammai omrim אומרים לו omrim lo לך חפור
שחוט וכסה. lech chapor shechot v'chaseh. Go dig, שחט shecht and cover.
ובית הלל אומרים u'Beis Hillel omrim לא ישחוט אלא אם כן היה
לו עפר מוכן מבעוד יום. lo yishchot ela im kein haya lo
afar muchan m'be'od yom. Don't שחט shecht if unless you have prepared
dirt. So what's the difference between what רב יוסף Rav Yosef said
and רבא Rava said? רבא Rava said that according to בית שמאי
Beis Shammai you'd say שחט, shecht, dig and cover, and רב יוסף
Rav Yosef said that בית שמאי Beis Shammai would say dig, שחט
shecht and cover. So what's the difference whether you tell him to
first dig the dirt or to first שחט shecht the animal? אמר
ליה אביי לרב יוסף, amar leh Abaye l'Rav Yosef, so אביי Abaye
wants to figure out why they formulated it differently. So he says
to רב יוסף: Rav Yosef: לימא מר ורבא בדבי רבי זירא אמר
רב קמיפלגי. leima mar v'Rava bid-Rabbi Zeira amar Rav kamiflegi. Maybe the
master, you רב יוסף Rav Yosef and רבא, Rava, בדבי רבי זירא
אמר רב bid-Rabbi Zeira amar Rav are arguing. The reason you're just
articulating בית שמאי Beis Shammai differently, either שחט, shecht dig, שחט shecht
dig and cover, or dig, שחט shecht and cover, what you're really
debating is a is a not a יום טוב Yom Tov question,
but in an issue about how to cover the blood and about
a position of
רבי זירא אמר רב. Rabbi Zeira amar Rav. דאמר רבי זירא אמר
רב, d'amar Rabbi Zeira amar Rav, because רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira says
in the name of רב, השוחט ha-shochet if you שחט shecht, חיה
או עוף chaya o of צריך שייתן עפר למטה ועפר למעלה. tzarich
she-yitein afar l'mata v'afar l'mala.
It's not enough to put dirt above the blood, you have to
have loose dirt below the blood as well. How do you know
it? שנאמר, she-ne'emar, the verse says, ושפך את דמו וכסהו בעפר, v'shaphach
et damo v'chiseihu be-afar, you will spill the blood
and you will cover it with dirt. עפר לא נאמר, afar lo
ne'emar, it doesn't say וכסהו
עפר, v'chiseihu afar, dirt will cover, אלא בעפר, ela be-afar, with dirt,
which means that the blood will be inside of the dirt, dirt
above it and dirt below it. Funny read of the verse. מלמד
שהשוחט צריך שייתן עפר למטה ועפר למעלה, melamed she-ha-shochet tzarich she-yitein afar
l'mata v'afar l'mala, above and below. So דמר, demar, the master, you
רב יוסף Rav Yosef who said dig, שחט shecht and then cover,
אית ליה דרבי זירא. it leh d'Rabbi Zeira. You hold of רבי
זירא. Rabbi Zeira. And therefore you're saying dig, put a layer of
of dirt below, then שחט shecht, and then cover again. So that's
רבי זירא's Rabbi Zeira position. ורבא, v'Rava, and רבא Rava who said
שחט, shecht dig and cover, לית ליה דרבי זירא, leit leh d'Rabbi
Zeira, doesn't hold of רבי זירא, Rabbi Zeira, so doesn't need there
to be soft loose dirt below and it's enough to put dirt
above. That's a pretty reasonable read of why they would articulate differently
when you're doing the digging. אמר ליה, amar leh, so רב יוסף
Rav Yosef said no. בין לדידי בין לרבא אית לן דרבי זירא.
bein l'didi bein l'Rava it lan d'Rabbi Zeira. Both I and רבא
Rava hold of רבי זירא, Rabbi Zeira, that you need to have
loose dirt below. And that's why, so it's understandable why I said
dig, שחט shecht. and cover. Why did רבא Rava say שחט, shecht
dig and cover? והכא בהא קמיפלגי. v'hacha be-ha kamiflegi. And here, here's
what we debate. רבא סבר Rava savar איכא עפר למטה אין אי
לא לא. ika afar l'mata in i lo lo. That actually even
according to בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, we will only allow him to
שחט shecht if there already is loose dirt there. But if there's
no loose dirt and he would have to dig to create the
layer of loose dirt, we won't let him שחט. shecht Now why
should that matter if we're going to let him dig to cover
the blood Why should we not let him dig to put on
the layer of loose dirt? For the following reason: דילמא מימלך ולא
שחט. Dilma mimrekh velo shakhet. What's he going to do? He'll dig,
he'll lay a loose layer of dirt, and then he'll say, you
know what, forget it, I'm not going to שחט shecht. this whole
animal, I'll just have some of my leftover chicken. And then
he'll have dug on יום טוב Yom Tov for no purpose. Okay?
So therefore, רבה Rabbah says
שחט shecht. only if you already have the loose dirt. I don't
want to let you dig. You need to have loose dirt below,
but I'm not going to let you do it if you don't
have it already ready because I'm afraid you'll do it and then
you'll change your mind. ובדידי Uvididi and I hold אדרבה adraba האי
עדיפא. ha'adifa. I'd rather you go ahead, dig, lay the layer of
dirt, and I'm willing to accept the risk that you might change
your mind. Why? Better to have that risk דלא שרי ליה dilo
shari lay because if I'm going to rule like רבה Rabbah and
I won't let you do it unless you already have a loose
layer of dirt, אתי לימנועי משמחת יום טוב, ati linu'ei misimchas Yom
Tov, then you're not going to שחט shecht when you want to
שחט. רבה's Rabbah making it harder for the guy to שחט. רבה's
Rabbah saying I'm not going to let him שחט unless there's already
a loose layer of dirt. Now all of this is debated within
בית שמאי. Beis Shammai. We actually don't פסקן pasken בית שמאי. Beis
Shammai. We פסקן pasken בית הלל, Beis Hillel, that בית הלל Beis
Hillel says don't do it לכתחילה lachatchila either, you know, in either
case. But within בית שמאי Beis Shammai that lets you do it
לכתחילה, lachatchila, they're debating whether that's only when there's already an existing
loose layer of dirt below. Okay, but that's within בית שמאי. Beis
Shammai. But בית הלל Beis Hillel says you can only do it
בדיעבד. b'di'eved. And what we'll do tomorrow is, you know, I'm just
we'll end here because it'll start a new topic, we'll do tomorrow
the question of why בדיעבד b'di'eved can you do it? Isn't it
violating the יום טוב Yom Tov to be digging a hole in
the ground?
Well, yeah, you don't need a shovel.
All right, so we'll see about that tomorrow. Okay.